<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>That great expedition for Ireland by way of underwriting proposed, by both Houses of Parliament, and graciously assented unto by His Maiesty is heere vindicated as pious, charitable, iust, politicke, profitable. And obiections to the contrary clearely answered, by one who heartily wisheth the speedy promotion of this proposition of underwriting, as almost the onely remedy.</title>
            <author>One who heartily wisheth the speedy promotion of this proposition of underwriting as almost the onely remedy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T839</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E83_37</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E137_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871663</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871663</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156487</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156487)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 14:E83[37], 24:E137[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>That great expedition for Ireland by way of underwriting proposed, by both Houses of Parliament, and graciously assented unto by His Maiesty is heere vindicated as pious, charitable, iust, politicke, profitable. And obiections to the contrary clearely answered, by one who heartily wisheth the speedy promotion of this proposition of underwriting, as almost the onely remedy.</title>
                  <author>One who heartily wisheth the speedy promotion of this proposition of underwriting as almost the onely remedy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Ioseph Hunscott,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156487:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156487:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THAT Great Expedition for IRELAND By way of underwriting propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by both Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and Graciouſly aſſented unto by His Majeſty is heere Vindicated As</p>
            <list>
               <item>Pious,</item>
               <item>Charitable,</item>
               <item>Iuſt,</item>
               <item>Politicke,</item>
               <item>Profitable.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And Obiections to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y clearely anſwered, by one who heartily wiſheth the ſpeedy promotion of this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of underwriting, as almoſt the onely remedy.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph Hunſcort.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156487:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156487:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y how much I was more affectionately apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the preſent calamities and deplorable eſtate of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and whileſt the voice of my friends there ſeemed to make one <hi>Chorus</hi> with the foules under the Altar, of them which were ſlaine for <note place="margin">Rev. 6. 10.</note> the Word of God, <hi>How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our bloud.</hi> So much the more this propoſition was unto me (if I may without preſumption make ſuch an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication) honey to my taſte, imuſick to mind eares, joy to mine heart: towards which, whileſt others offer great ſummes, give mo leave to caſt my mite into the treaſury, and becauſe I cannot ſubſcribe as a cotracter, permit me yet to ſubſcribe as an inſurer.</p>
            <p>Theſe Iriſh <hi>Eſaus</hi> have long expected ſuch a day, though like <note place="margin">Lupus eſt &amp; tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens &amp; fremens. Aug.</note> burnt children they dreaded the fire, but a woolfe whether he be fearful or furious is ſtill a woolfe. Now when they thought they had their opportunity, (what I write is moſt certain) and that they had committed us together, like the Lion and the Bore in the Greek Apollogiſt, they hoped well that they with the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture might ſteal away the prey from both parties. But this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill quickly same the courage of the Rebels and abate the triumphs and inſultations of the Popiſh partie. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> concurrence of all degrees of men will ſoon change their <hi>Harp</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 30. 31.</note> 
               <hi>into mourning, and their Organs into the voice of them that weep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if there were a revolution of the great <hi>Platonicall</hi> yeare, thoſe dayes ſeeme to be reinuned wherein the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their free will offerings, towards the making and adoming <note place="margin">Exod. 36.</note> of the Tabernacle; or the Conſulate of <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> &amp; <hi>Marcellus</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the overthrow of <hi>Cannoe,</hi> when the Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> emptied their private Coffers, to ſupply the preſſing neceſſities of that State. They know that the publick may ſubſiſt without the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare but the private never without the publick. This alone gave that Citie the advantage of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and the prehemineace of the whole world, onely the want of this (to forbeare nearer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances) was the ruine of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which made the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> laugh to finde ſuch poore enemies, and rich captives.</p>
            <p>It is thought there were two ſpeciall remorahs which did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarde the proſperous ſucceſſe of the late Iriſh wars. The one was ſlow and ſhort ſupplies, coming like <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice in proceſſe <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 3.</note> of time, and in ſuch a thriſty unthriſty way, that they loſt an hog for an half penie worth of Tar. It is a great fault in Client
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156487:3"/>
to ſtarve his cauſe, but worſe in a State. I know not whether it have been the fate or fortune of our late expeditions, that ſtill our wings wanted impinge, juſt when we ſhould have made an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious flight. Our late renowned <hi>Deborah,</hi> Q <hi>Eliz</hi> being much perplexed with the bad ſucceſſe of her Iriſh affaires, ſent over that expert Commander Sir <hi>Roger Williams</hi> to find out the true reaſon thereof; who returned her Majeſty a true report veiled in this homely ſtory, of an Oxford man that bought a gooſe in <hi>Dublin</hi> for a groat, and a penie fagot to roſt his gooſe, but his fagot was conſumed by that time the gooſe was well warmed, ſo of neceſſitie he was to buy another fagot, which made his gooſe begin to drop; and after that a third fagot: but becauſe it cooled between fagot and fagot, his gooſe was little better: Then the man grew angry, and bought a whole g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oats worth of fagots together, and roſted his gooſe well in the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an hand. The application is eaſie.</p>
            <p>The other rub was conceived to be the too much correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between ſome of the Commanders and the Earle of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone, who would not ſtick in private to brag to themſelves, how much they were beholden to him. Surgeons often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long their cures, and beggers ordinarily nouriſh their fores for advantage. It would trouble a mans mind to hazard his life, and for his reward thruſt himſelfe out of all his imployment, unleſſe he might be ſure either of triumph at his returne, or a good Dividend out of the ſpoiles: Both theſe inconveniences will be removed by this contract; The warre will not coole betweene one ſupplie and another; the great and inferiour Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers will themſelves become adventurers, which is a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of great weight, able to inſpire valour into a pale-liverd coward, when (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Catilines</hi> Souldiers) <hi>Divitias decus glorians libertatem patriam in dextris portunt:</hi> When men beare their countrey, their riches, their portions, and their hopes in their right hands.</p>
            <p>In a word, this propoſition is a center wherein all the lines of Piety, Charity, Juſtice, Policy, and Utilitie do meet together. Hence is a cord not onely threefold, but fivefold, almoſt as double as <hi>Ajax</hi> his ſhield.</p>
            <p>Firſt for pietie, he that had viewed the beaten wayes to their Maſſe-houſes, and the narrow paths to our Churches, in the moſt parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> might juſtly have taken up that of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156487:3"/>
Prophet <hi>Jeremy, The wayes of Sion do mourn, becauſe no man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>to the ſolemne Aſſemblies.</hi> Of that of our Saviour, <hi>Wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, &amp;c. Strait is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 7. 13.</note> 
               <hi>the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth unto life, &amp;c.</hi> But this courſe if it be purſued, will ſpread Religion throughout the whole Kingdom in an inſtant, as the lightning which ſhineth in the Eaſt, and appeareth in the Weſt. Next after the glory of God, <hi>hallowed be thy Name,</hi> we are taught to pray for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of Religion <hi>thy Kingdom come:</hi> When the owner heard that the Lord had need of his goods, he preſently let them go. <note place="margin">Matt. 21. 3.</note> If there were no certain expectation of profit, yet in this caſe we ought to offer freely, and bleſſe God who hath given us means and hearts to lend unto him ſome part of his own ſtore. When <hi>Solomon</hi> beſtowed ſuch an infinite maſſe of treaſure upon <note place="margin">1 Chron. 29. 16. 1 King. 10. 27,</note> the Temple, yet we read that ſilver was as common as ſtones in Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>Next for charity. It was not without cauſe, when the Lord offered <hi>David</hi> his choiſe of three plagues, that he prayed, <hi>Let me fall into the hand of the Lord, but not into the hands of men.</hi> Their <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24, 14.</note> mercies are cruell; ſure I am, the Iriſh mercies have been very cruell, like the mercies of a prevailing coward, in cold blood to be cruell, without provocation to be cruell, to be cruell to that ſex and that age (women and little ones) whom God would <note place="margin">Deut. 20. 14.</note> have ſpared even after peace, is rejected. To be cruell (extreme cruell) to that unarmed profeſſion, which ſhould it ſelf be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, the Miniſters of the Word of God, yet the garriſon of the Philiſtines did not hurt the colledge of the Prophets. But for theſe butcheries there can be no reparation, <hi>Numb.</hi> 35. 31. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">1 Sam. 10. 5.</note> the blood of the murtherer, he that ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, without which the Land can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be cleanſed from the guilt of innocent blood; nay to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell <note place="margin">Numb. 35. 33.</note> even to the very fruit-trees, which God expreſly forbiddeth. To be cruell to the very wals and roofes, which the civill hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <note place="margin">Deut. 20. 19.</note> did abominate. <hi>Tully</hi> cals it <hi>nefarium bellum,</hi> a wicked warre, which is made with wals, and roofes, and pillars. And <hi>Livy</hi> commends the Romanes, that having taken <hi>Capua,</hi> they did not tirraniſe over the wals and houſes. But it ſeemes theſe men deſpaire to hold them themſelves, and they would not have them to become receptacles for us. All this while I ſpeak not of thoſe goods and moveables which they took from the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156487:4"/>
Proteſtants, which in the ſpace of ten weeks were ſtimated by a moderate ſurvey at ten hundred thouſad pounds. Then if it be a bleſſed thing to them to receive, what a bleſſing will this be to joyn with others in the reliefe of ſo many deſolate widows, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed orphans, &amp; baniſhed perſos. That very day that <hi>Zacheus</hi> made ſuch a proffer, he heard, <hi>This day is divation come to thine houſe.</hi> And this likewiſe will be a ſecond fruit of thy ſubſcriptio.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for Juſtice, There are three grounds of a juſt warre. Firſt, The defence and protection of the innocent. Secondly, The recovery and repetition of things wrongfully deteined. Thirdly, The puniſhment and revenge of injuries received. Here all theſe conſiderations or rather obligations do concur; The perſons to be protected, are brethren by Nation, by Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and by the ſame bond of ſubjection under a gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne. The things deteined are their lands, their goods, their wives, their children, their friends, and whatſoever a man can call deare in this world: And not deteined onely, but abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, famiſhed, ſtarved, and uſed worſe than dogs. The injuries received are of all ſorts, reflecting both upon ſoul, and body, and eſtate. So this Contract is pious, charitable, and juſt.</p>
            <p>In the fourth place, it ſtands with the rules of good Policie. Is it not one cauſe of our diſtemper, that the head wants a due proportion of aliment, and is neceſſitated out of proper courſe <hi>ſequi pabulum?</hi> Now in reſpect <hi>Vlster</hi> is the loweſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and moſt planted, and by conſequence the leaſt expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Eſcheats there, by a probable <hi>Medium,</hi> which cannot much erre, this Million of money to be contracted for, will not take up above 25 or 2600000 of Engliſh Acres; and out of this will ariſe to his Majeſtie a conſtant yeerly Revenue of 23000. l. or thereabout: To which all the reſt of the Eſcheated Lands being added, and improved in like manner, it will raiſe ſuch a conſiderable Revenue as may in a great part eaſe the Subject of extraordinarie Subſidies.</p>
            <p>The poorer ſort are yet ſenſible of the late charge of Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Poll-money, This courſe will free them, and transfer the burthen upon ſuch as are both able and willing to undergo it, this will much quicken and accelerate the ſupplies; leſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are more capable of ſudden motions; By this means <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhall be ſpeedily reſcued before it be loſt out-right. If our enemies had the command of that back-doore, we ſhould not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156487:4"/>
long want them here. When the <hi>Romanes</hi> had once gotten <hi>Sicily,</hi> they ſoon after invaded and gave Laws to <hi>Africke.</hi> You remember the old Proverbe, He that will <hi>England</hi> win, with <hi>Ireland</hi> muſt begin. Let us defend <hi>Aras &amp; focos,</hi> our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, our Religion, rather at a diſtance than at home. This will amplifie and extend the power and glory of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation: whileſt trees grow in a throng, on an heap, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpread out their bowes at libertie, as they may do when they are removed and planted at a greater diſtance. There are two reaſons why Rome did flouriſh more and longer than Athens or Sparta; the one by incorporating thoſe whom they conquered with themſelves, as the Sabines and the Albanes, by this meanes changing enemies into Citizens, which courſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded proſperouſly to <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, in the union of Wales to England. The other was their Colonies which they ſent abroad: when Rome was the Miſtreſſe of a great part of the world, their chiefeſt ſtrength was in their Colonies, out of which the greateſt part of their Armies were ever raiſed, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſubſidio imperium populi Romani ſtetit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Livie,</hi> If this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 27.</note> proceed with effect, I doubt not ſpeedily to find another England in Ireland, and to ſee that old ſaying proved falſe, Ireland will not be reformed till the day of judgement. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Plantations ſell by drops here and there, <hi>Rari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>autes in gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gite vaſto,</hi> (that was the reaſon why ſo many of the old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh degenerated and turned Iriſh.) They could not operate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſpheere of their own activity, but this by the bleſſing of God will preſently give a ſettlement both to it ſelf, and that Kingdom. Hitherto a great part of thoſe who have gone over, have been poore Farmers, or neceſſitous perſons, that were not able to make a conſiderable improvement. Theſe contracters will be able to make it a gallant Kingdom forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. So you ſee Religion, Charitie, Juſtice, and Policy, are foure great incouragements to ſubſcribe this Contract.</p>
            <p>But yet there is one wanting which is as much looked after in the world as any of them, that is, the ſmell of gaine, <hi>Quid dabitur viro?</hi> What advantage ſhall a Contracter reape by it? If there be a concurrence of this alſo, <hi>Omne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulit punctum qui mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet utile dulci.</hi> Yes ſurely, be it ſpoken with all due ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the All-mighty providence, in whoſe hand is the event of battells, and by his grace and bleſſing upon the juſt Armes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156487:5"/>
of his Royall Majeſtie, and his loyall Subjects, I doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the adventure to be much greater than a voyage into the Weiles, eſpecially if we beginne with ſpeed before they get forraine ayde, and not a velitation but a juſt warre.</p>
            <p>It was the <hi>Spartane</hi> errour, that with Skirmiſhes rather than Battells, they taught the <hi>Thebans</hi> to become their Maſters. Now if a man would ſet out one hundred pounds for the inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of another, which were a great proportion, conſidering the adventure, yet the contract would beare it over and over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. To ſpeak modeſtly within my compaſſe, That w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> might have beene ſold for ſixe thouſand pounds within this yeare, a Contracter ſhall now have for leſſe than one thouſand pounds, beſides the expectation of a mightie improvement by this plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. So as it is cleerely the moſt gainefull trade that can be driven in this Kingdome in theſe dead times, and more ſecure than that which is <hi>rudentibus apta,</hi> which hanges upon Cable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes, where his ſacred Majeſtie, the honourable members of both Houſes of Parliament, and the whole body of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are ſo deeply ingaged in the inſurance. So I may twiſt this fifth threed of Profit, with the other foure, of Religion, Charitie, Juſtice, and Policy.</p>
            <p>But weake eyes are offended with the light of the Sunne, Though this Contract be never ſo pious, charitable, juſt, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to the publick State, to private Contracters, yet the tooth of envie will not want ſomething to bite at, nor the tongue of malice to barke at.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they ſay, Chriſt never planted Religion in bloud, when the Diſciples demanded leave to call for fire from Heaven, to deſtroy the Cities that did not receive them, our Saviour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Yee know not what ſpirit yee are of.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk 9. 54.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer in the firſt place, that this warre is not meerly as they would make the world beleeve, a warre of Religion, but mixt with other conſiderations. I omit the native and heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary love of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> as to the root from whence they ſpring. I paſſe by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Penſioners in <hi>Ireland,</hi> among whom the Romiſh tributary Archbiſhop of <hi>Caſhell</hi> was not long ſince queſtioned for one, and diſmiſſed meerly for his ſimplicitie, as a more probable enemy to a cup of Uſquebah than to a State. Yet I heare and feare that the party who was imployed to apprehend him, hath ſince loſt his bloud for that <note place="margin">D. S. P.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:156487:5"/>
ſervice. But I cannot omit a Treaty in <hi>Spaine</hi> about two yeares ſince, between ſome of the greateſt inſtruments of State there and ſundry <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, wherein it was propoſed by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> party, what revenue, what proviſion for ſhipping, what other <note place="margin">This ſtory is in the Clerk of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels books in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> advantage <hi>Ireland</hi> would bring to his Catholick Majeſty, and how facile it was to gaine it; how the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſtood affected to him. It is well knowne to ſome perſons of great eminency both in <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> who were preſent at this conſultation, what was their reſolution, to imploy two Fryers with Letters of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thither, to a great number of the Nobilitie and Gentry of that Kingdome as well <hi>Iriſh</hi> as old <hi>Engliſh.</hi> (I confeſſe the choice argued no depth of underſtanding,) The Fryers are knowne, the perſons to whom they were to addreſſe themſelves are knowne, and if it had not been for ſome accidentall troubles, they had been apprehended, or eſcaped narrowly. If you ask how I know this, Suppoſe one of the Fryers was as big with the ſecret as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> his Barber, and forfeare of burſting did vent himſelf among ſome rootes of reeds, which after made the diſcovery. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is moſt true. So you ſee there is ſomething more in it than Religion.</p>
            <p>I have ſeene a Letter from the late Earle of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Terconnell,</hi> to the now Cardinall Protector <hi>Barberino,</hi> wherein they profeſſe that though they did for a time ſuperſede from their right in <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet they did not intend to deſert it. I have ſeene another Letter from a company of meane and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible perſons, ſaving that they had ſome old <hi>Iriſh</hi> bloud in them, to the ſame Cardinall Protector, wherein they ſtyle themſelves <hi>Barones</hi> and <hi>Dinastae,</hi> Nobles and Peeres of the Realme. This ſhewed they had not forgotten their Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors pretenſes; but here was nothing of Religion in it. I have ſeene two Letters of late dated from Sir <hi>Philomy O Neale</hi> and his brother <hi>Tirlogh,</hi> ſince they were in rebellion, to two emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Gentlemen of the Scottiſh Nation, wherein they offer and deſire not onely quarter but friendſhip, alledging this reaſon, that both Nations were one in their originall, and intreating that they might continue ſo in affection: I urge not this as though thoſe Gentlemen did credit it, but to ſhew that there is more in their deſignes than Religion, otherwiſe they would have ſought other Confederates.</p>
            <p>I might adde thoſe Propheſies which of late did flie abroad familiarly among them; as that of the three Cockes, the red
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156487:6"/>
Cocke and the blacke, which continued wounding one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till the white Cocke (whereby they denoted the Earle of <hi>Tyrone)</hi> came and deſtroyed them both. Theſe people had their thoughts taken up with ſomething elſe than Religion. Surely if there had been nothing in it but Religion, they would never have perſwaded a Gentleman to goe to Maſſe, upon aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of life, and preſently when he had done it, have hanged him up, ſo farre as was in them to kill both body and ſoule; yet thus wee heare from all hands they uſed Maſter <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aletor.</hi> Surely if it be Religion, it is ſuch a Religion as that of the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemites, Shall not their cattle and their ſubſtance be ours?</hi> Shall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <note place="margin">Gen. 34. 23.</note> then become a cloake or a ſtalking horſe for thoſe who robbe and burne and raviſh and kill unarmed enemies? Were all our houſes, Townes, ſtackyards, heretickes, that they were condemned to be burned?</p>
            <p>This is moſt certaine, that every one of the Rebells upon the firſt inſurrection, did ſeiſe all thoſe Lands which his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or his grand-father, or his great grand-father had held before <hi>Tyrones</hi> Warres, or before the Artainder of <hi>Shane O Neale,</hi> although all theſe were inveſted in the Crowne by Act of Parliament 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and have ſince been quietly poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed builded and planted by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> There is no queſtion, but this was the Religion which they thirſted after. Their debts were great, their fortunes and eſtates deſperate, even ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally. They had no other way left to repaire themſelves but this. And yet our old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentry in the pale, are ſo dull as to be fooled with this groſſe conceite, that this warre is onely for Religion. Let them take heed, their Land is the flower of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The old <hi>Iriſh</hi> have the ſame pretenſes to it which they have to the reſt, and if it ſhould come to that, they would finde by wofull experience, that the goodneſſe of the ſoyle would much inflame their devotion. What favour could they expect in ſuch a caſe, but that which <hi>Polyphemus</hi> promiſed to <hi>Ulyſſes.</hi> That he ſhould be the laſt devoured?</p>
            <p>Though they have an equall appetite unto both, yet we and they together have been too much for the ſtomack to digeſtat one meale. Admit they are confederate with them, have they not offered the ſame termes to the <hi>Scots?</hi> But they were not ſo credulous to be gulled by them. My hope is that my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men ſhall buy their repentance at a readier market.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:156487:6"/>
            <p>But to take their caſe at the beſt, admitting, but not granting that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> warre of religion. There is a vaſt diſtance betweene theſe two, to plant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eligion with the ſword, which whether, or how far it be lawfull, is no way pertinent to this preſent caſe, and to protect true pietie againſt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious vanitie, to defend Orthodox Chriſtians from Heterodox Papiſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyall Subjects from rebellious Traytours, <hi>To breake the jawes of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 29. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>wicked, and to plucke the ſpoyle out of his teeth.</hi> Shall it bee lawfull for them, being but Subjects, to uſurp the inſeparable rights of the Crowne, to trample upon the Lawes of the Land, to purſue the religion eſtabliſhed by Parliament with fire and ſword, to overthrow totally the proprietie of the Subject: and ſhall it not bee lawfull for his Majeſtie to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Himſelfe, Religion, his Lawes, his Subjects? It is true, this war may concerne Religion in the conſequents, otherwiſe I ſhould be right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, but antecedently in it ſelfe it is no war of religion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is objected, that the Proteſtants beyond ſeas will ſmart for this, that this courſe will deprive his Majeſtie of all power to mediate for them, and take away that correſpondence which is obſerved betweene Princes in point of ſtate.</p>
            <p>It will not be needfull in this caſe to conſider, whether toleration or connivence in religion may be admitted, or of whom, with what cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and conditions, whether it extend to the perſons only, or to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice alſo, who are tares in the Lords field, how far theſe tares may be, or muſt be ſuffered. Whether <hi>Iuſtine</hi> the Emperour of Conſtantinople did well, to ſurceaſe from perſecuting the Arrians in his Dommions, upon the humble ſuit of the Orthodox Chriſtians in Italy, who groaned then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the perſecution of <hi>Theodorick</hi> their King, an Arrian Prince, nor how far this hiſtorie may be applyable to theſe times. It is ſufficient to anſwer this objection, to ſhew that the Iriſh are not called to an account for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but for robberies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rapes, murthers, treaſons. If ever Proteſtants ſhall make themſelves ſo unworthy, ſo uncapable of any mediation, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant peccata</hi> let them ſuffer according to their demerits, and let no eye pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is objected, that this courſe will prolong the war, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Rebels, when they are excluded from all hope of pardon, that it will hinder all accommodations whereas now they offer to come in upon termes, that it will make the conqueſt more difficult, that it will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all meanes of reparation from the poore Proteſtants, who are rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and ſtripped, and have no hopes of ſatisfaction, but out of the lands
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156487:7"/>
ſom of the arch Rebels, that it tyeth his Majeſties hands from pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whom he pleaſeth, and abridgeth the power of the chiefe Governer, diſabling him from rewarding good ſervitours; that it were a ſafer way to take in the greater part upon ſubmiſſion, and afterwards to puniſh them inſenſibly, and by degrees.</p>
            <p>This argument is more ſpecious than ſubſtantiall, in true reaſon this courſe will rather ſhorten the war, when the enemies ſhall ſee that they are not like to be dallied, or to be trifled withall, it will ſoone humble them and make them preſent themſelves with ſack-cloth upon their loyns, <note place="margin">1. Kin. 20 32</note> and ropes upon their heads, as the Syrians did to the King of Iſrael. So thoſe who have been drawne into action, by feare or fained ſhewes, may leave objects of his Majeſties grace, either for the pardon of their lives, or reſtitution to their eſtates, according to their reſpective deſerts, or the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour they ſhall find in his royall eyes; and yet thoſe be left to exemplarie juſtice, whoſe black outragious villanies have rendred them, even in the judgement of their owne conſciences, uncapable of all favour. Whoſe lands being eſcheated, will be able to counter-balance this fumme, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion contracted for. And yet I think no man will be ſo vaine, to ask how then ſhall this great ſumme be employed, whilſt this Crowne and Kingdome are ſo far engaged in debts, whilſt the poore rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Proteſtants cry for reparation, and this bloudy rebellion hath ſhewed us how neceſſarie it is to have ſome more places of ſtrength in Ireland. If they meane any other accommodation than this, I underſtand it not, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they would have us, who have eſcaped their Butcherly hands to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne among them, and gently to hold out our throats to be cut at their diſcretion. Who will not rather chuſe to forſake his eſtate there, and beg an halfe-penny from paſſengers with <hi>Beliſarius,</hi> than after ſo evident a demonſtration of their univerſall rancour, to expoſe himſelfe and his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to their barbarous crueltie? If they were only thornes in our ſides to vex us, as the Canaanites were to the Iſraelites, it were more tolerable; <note place="margin">Num. 33. 25.</note> but to be skenes in our ſides to murther us, is worſe. No, no, there is no thought to be had of an Engliſh mans abode in Ireland, without the wals of a Citie, unleſſe the Kingdome may be reduced to a better temperature and conſtitution. Wee often ſee a feaveriſh diſtemper uſhers in a better habitude of the body. Now is the time when it may be affected with ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but after a free pardon, that which is juſtice now would become murther. Now is the time when their forraine Confederates have their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156487:7"/>
hands full at home, and can afford them no great ſtore of reliefe. All wiſe and flouriſhing Kingdomes and Common-wealths, have ever made choyſe to undergoe a preſent charge, rather than a future and perpetuall inconvenience. Neither will this project either give impediment to the reparation of thoſe who are robbed and damnified, ſeeing that if the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels ſubmit, they may be repaired out of the ſumme contracted for, and if they ſtand out, there will be as much more land for them, upon the like rent; and yet ſufficient left over and above both theſe proportions, to be diſpoſed unto good ſervitours.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is ſaid that this way is cruell, and tends not to a reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but to an utter extirpation, that it doth involve the nocent and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in the ſame puniſhment, That it were better to offer conditions <note place="margin">Deut. 20. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of peace, and then let the obſtinate ſuffer. I anſwer with Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Graviſſimus nodus, &amp;c.</hi> An hard knot muſt have an hard wedge. When <hi>Titus,</hi> the darling of mankind, ſaw the infinite mortalitie which accompanyed the ſiege of Ieruſalem, by famine, peſtilence, and the ſword, hee wept, and caſting up his eyes to Heaven, called God to witneſſe, that hee was innocent of thoſe miſeries. So his Majeſtie may juſtly ſay, that whatſoever they ſuffer, they may thank themſelves for it, Hee and his Kingdome are guiltleſſe of all the bloud that is ſhed <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3. 28</note> for ever, eſpecially ſince they have yet time of grace, the red flag is yet up of mercie, mixt with juſtice; the black flag of utter ruine and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not yet advanced, yet they have time to remove and flit from under the ſigne of the Sword, to be under the ſigne of the Crowne, to uſe Saint <hi>Anſelmes</hi> compariſon. If they fall, they fall wilfully into the pit which themſelves have digged; they have firſt unſheathed the ſword, or rather, they have ſheathed it in the bowels of innocents, and left their carkaſſes as dung upon the face of the earth; Can they imagine that theſe doe not cry for vengeance? If the ſame ſword take his courſe about, and themſelves feele the laſhes of <hi>Bellona's</hi> bloudy whip, whom can they blame? They have malitiouſly deſtroyed the good creatures of God and made willfull waſt of his bleſſings, and offered the come of whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries for a ſacrifice to the fire. Now if famine puniſh exceſſe, if wofull want follow wilfull waſte, if others mete the ſame meaſure againe into their boſomes, preſſed downe and running over, if condemnation merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe light on thoſe that ſhewed not mercy, whom can they condemne? I confeſſe no vertue makes a man more like his Creatour then mercy, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156487:8"/>
there is a terrible lenity, a ſparing cruelty, a fooliſh pitty, that is, when indulgence to the bad becomes cruelty to the good. When demerit and neceſſity doe both concurre, there puniſhment was never yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſeverity. But that the innocent ſhould bee extirpated, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, be that far from the Throne of my Soveraigne. Reward and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment (as ſaid <hi>Lycurgus)</hi> doe preſerve the Common-wealth. And theſe two have two ſutable Ojbects, Well-doers, Ill-doers; The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrares care muſt be not to miſtake either the Act or the Object, as Death and <hi>Cupid</hi> are fained to have done their Bowes, which made ſo many old doting Lovers; and young herſes, that he inflict not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment upon good doers (the teares of Innocents are more dangerous then any deluge) nor faſten rewards upon the Nocent; He that juſtifieth the wicked is an abhomination to the Lord. Nay rather it is to be wiſhed by all good Chriſtians, that even thoſe who are not tranſcendently nocent may find favour, at leaſt for life, and principally thoſe who (as God pleades for the <hi>Ninivites, cannot diſcerne betweene their right hand and their left,</hi> but alwaies with this caution, ſo farre as it may conſiſt with the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nah. 4. 11.</note> ſecurity of the good Subject.</p>
            <p>Charity pleades for pardon, except it be where a greater charity pleades againſt it. I onely propoſe a <hi>quaere</hi> (I preſume not to apply) why the more ſtubborne and refractory ſort of guilty perſons, and yet not Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of ſedition, may not be removed from their native ſoyle, as the Romans dealt with the <hi>Ligurians</hi> a rebellious people, that if they will bee ſitting upon the <hi>Cockatrices</hi> eggs of miſchiefe and Treaſon, yet as the <hi>Florentine</hi> ſaid they may never hatch them, being ſo far from their neſts. In our memory, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> thought feare of danger a juſt ground to baniſh all the Moores out of his Kingdome, here both danger and deſert concur to make it lawfull. Others who are more apt to bee conformed, may be partly diſperſed in <hi>England,</hi> and partly continued in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo as they aſſume Engliſh names, weare Engliſh Apparrell, ſpeake the Engliſh Language, inhabite Engliſh houſes, and above all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Religion proteſted in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto the Romiſh Prieſts have preſerved theſe markes of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a wall of ſeparation to prevent an Union; hereafter let it be as capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall for a Prieſt to come there, as it was for an armed Engliſh-man to bee ſeene in <hi>Callis.</hi> I confeſſe ſome <hi>Iriſh</hi> have done good ſervice againſt the Rebells, theſe deſerve to bee rewarded: I confeſſe in ſome places the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156487:8"/>
chiefeſt abuſes were acted &amp; committed by the meaner ſort of people. But do we beleeve it was ordinarily done without the conſent, nay without the command of their Land-lords? It is ſcarce credible to thoſe who know the abſolute power of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lord over his dependents, why did they not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainthem where they could, <hi>Qui deſinit obviare cum poteſt, conſentit.</hi> The <hi>Benjamites</hi> refuſing to puniſh the guilty perſons were proſecuted the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: plotters and contrivers, I adde alſo concealers and ſmotherers of <note place="margin">Judg. 20. 13.</note> this horrid Treaſon, deſerve as much to bee puniſhed as the Actors and Executers, or rather more, as being commonly more eminent, and more dangerous. It was <hi>Tarquins</hi> ſilent, but in that caſe unjuſt advice to his Sonne, when with his Rod hee ſtrake off the heads of the Poppies. It was the juſt practiſe of the Romans upon the tumultuous <hi>Ardeates,</hi> the rebellious <hi>Cyprians,</hi> and many others. It would be known what was that good ſucceſſe which was faſted and prayed for weekely in publike, before this plot was diſcovered, and who were preſent at that meeting, or privy to it; where it was queſtioned how this buſineſſe ſhould bee managed, ſome adviſing that the Engliſh ſhould be kindly uſed, onely their Forts and ſtrengths be ſeiſed; others that they ſhould bee ſtripped and turned out of all; others that they ſhould not onely be ſtripped, but Maſſacred: All which were followed in ſeverall parts. It brings to my mind the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which <hi>Heremius</hi> gave to <hi>Pontius</hi> the Captaine of the <hi>Samnites,</hi> when he had the Romans in a ſtraite, either to diſmiſſe them all with love, which would produce an honourable peace, or elſe to kill them to to one man, <hi>Dead men bite not.</hi> But <hi>Pontius</hi> tooke a middle and moſt pernicious courſe to himſelfe, firſt to abuſe them baſely, and then to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe them, irritating thereby a powerfull enemy to the ruine of the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites.</hi> Laſtly, conditions of peace are to bee offered to forraine Enemies; but to bee petitioned and ſued for by domeſtick Rebells. If they deſire Peace, in the firſt place let them deliver up to Juſtice the heads, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of the Rebellion, as the Citizens of <hi>Abell</hi> did <hi>Shebah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bickrs,</hi> and the Lands, Forts and Goods, which they detaine unjuſtly, and then come in and ſubmit themſelves to his Majeſties Grace. This is the onely way left them to obtaine mercy.</p>
            <p>There is one Objection more, that the event of Warre is doubtfull, That it is not comely to ſell the Beares skin before the beaſt is killed.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, it is not good to fiſh too far before the Net, nor to boaſt preſumptuouſly of to morrow, <hi>for wee know not what a day may bring forth;</hi> And therefore let not him that girdeth on his harneſie, boaſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156487:9"/>
himſelfe as hee that putteth it off. The eleven Tribes had the bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 10. 11. Iudg. 20.</note> cauſe, and did much exceed the <hi>Benjamites</hi> in numerous preparation, yet it was the Will of God they ſhould be beaten in two Battells. But that was before the eleven Tribes had humbled themſelves before the Lord, ſo it be done without preſumptuous pride, with a due ſubmiſſion to the Will of God, placing our chiefeſt confidence, not in our owne ſtrength, but in his bleſſing: I doe not ſee what can be taxed in it, for manifeſting whereof I onely lay downe theſe two concluſions.</p>
            <p>Firſt that ſpoiles in a juſt War and Eſcheats of rebellious Subjects were ever held lawfull, it was <hi>Iſraels</hi> Legacy to <hi>Ioſeph: I give thee one portion</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 48. 22</note> 
               <hi>above thy Brethren, which I tooke out of the hand of the</hi> Amerites <hi>with my Sword and with my Bow:</hi> The Law is generall, <hi>Thou ſhalt take unto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 20. 14.</note> 
               <hi>thy ſelfe, and thou ſhalt eate the ſpoile of thine enemie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the dividing and apportioning of the ſpoile before hand is grounded upon the ſame reaſon and equity, with the judiciall Law of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for the dividing of the ſpoiles. <hi>Numb.</hi> 31. 37. And with thoſe rules for dividing the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> before it was conquered. <hi>Num.</hi> 34. So I conclude, notwithſtanding all Objections, that this contract is pious, charitable, juſt, politick, and profitable; And though I will not make the ſubſcription or not ſubſcription thereof, to bee like <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> and <hi>Sibboleth,</hi> a marke to diſtinguiſh betweene an <hi>Ephraimite</hi> and a <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadite:</hi> yet as in the body natural, when any member is ill-affected, all the bad humours flow unto it, and on the other ſide when any part needeth aliment, the good humours have recourſe thither; ſo let that union and conjunction which is among the Rebels to deſtroy the body of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, teach all loyall Subjects with mutuall and reciprocall affection to indeavour the preſervation thereof. My heart is towards the Governours of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which offered themſelves willingly among the people. <hi>Iudges</hi> 5. 9.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
